this video and the next discuss weight
bias and discrimination which may be a
sensitive topic uh for many people
how does this play out in health care
watch to find out more about this
important topic
[Music]
described as the last acceptable form of
bias
weight stigma is the rampant
discrimination and stereotyping of
overweight individuals
50 overweight women were asked to keep a
diary of all the times they felt they
were being stigmatized for their weight
over a single week more than a thousand
instances were recorded an overweight
woman may expect to be harassed such as
called names or insulted run into
physical barriers like unable to fit
into public seats or discriminated
against such as perceived poor service
at restaurants or stores on average
about three times a day
obese men report three times less
discrimination than women of the same
size so maybe it's only a daily
occurrence for them
they're not just being paranoid studies
using professional actors presenting as
job applicants made up to appear
overweight with the hollywood magic of
theatrical prostheses
were significantly more likely to be
discriminated against than when
appearing as their normal weight selves
this employment bias was found to be
especially prejudice against overweight
women compared to men
attitudes can also be explored in
surveys in a comparison of 16
stigmatized social groups such as
homosexuals and homeless people only
drug addicts and smokers were regarded
with higher levels of disgust than obese
individuals
the researchers did note however there
was effectively a tie
obese people were quote unquote rated
just as disgusting as politicians
this weight stigma starts surprisingly
young
children as young as three years old
describe overweight peers as mean stupid
lazy and ugly
then
there was that famous study published
back in 1961.
children in summer camps and schools
across a swath of different social
cultural and ethnic backgrounds in
california montana and new york were
asked to rank the following images as to
who they liked best including a child
and crutches with a brace on their leg a
child in a wheelchair a child with one
of their hands missing a facially
disfigured child or
an obese child
in every population of kids they tested
there was remarkable uniformity
the obese child always came in
dead last
yeah that was ages ago though
but in 2003 researchers published the
40-year follow-up
the study was repeated and
the title of the study gives it away
the stigmatization of obese children
getting
worse
the obese child was like even less
this parallels trends throughout society
with nearly a 70 jump in perceived
weight discrimination recorded in
national surveys since the mid-90s
attitudes among teachers may not be
helping more than a quarter of teachers
and other school staff surveyed felt
that becoming obese is one of the worst
things that could happen to a person
even parents can be biased providing
less support for college for their
overweight daughters compared to thinner
siblings as two prominent obesity
researchers commented it is a strong
prejudice indeed
when parents discriminate against their
own children
what about doctors
one representative national survey found
that more than half of physicians viewed
obese patients as awkward unattractive
ugly and non-compliant
about a quarter of nurses agreed or
strongly agreed to the statement caring
for an obese patient usually repulses me
this antagonism can have serious health
consequences for those who may need it
the most for example obese women are at
higher risk for developing cervical
endometrial and ovarian cancers yet they
are less likely to be screened
morbidly obese patients only have about
half the odds of getting their
recommended pelvic exams
part of this may be avoidance on the
part of the patient but some doctors
just turn obese patients away
the sun sentinel pulled ob gyn practices
in florida and found that as many as one
in seven refused to see heavier women
for example setting weight cut-offs for
new patients starting at 200 pounds
even doctors who welcome obese patients
have been found to give them short
shrift
physicians randomized to receive a
medical chart of a migraine patient who
was either presented as average weight
overweight or obese
said that they would give the obese
patient about 28 less of their time
and it's less quality time
recorded doctors visits found physicians
tend to build less emotional rapport
with overweight patients
even obesity specialists profess
increasingly explicit anti-fat attitudes
worsening in surveys taken between 2001
and 2013 obesity specialists described
fat people as significantly more lazy
stupid
and worthless
even in the medical literature you'll
find lines like this an example from the
annals of internal medicine obesity is
an aesthetic crime
it is ugly
the good news is they appear to be able
to hide their disdain
in a study entitled obese patients
overestimate physicians attitudes of
respect despite the negative attitudes
doctors harbored towards their obese
patients the same patients expressed
their satisfaction with their providers
the researchers concluded while
physicians may be successfully playing
the part the lack of true respect
suggests the authenticity of the patient
physician relationship
should be questioned
[Music]
you